<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The princess of Monpensier written originally in French, and now newly rendered into English.</title>
            <title>Princesse de Monpensier. English</title>
            <author>La Fayette, Madame de (Marie-Madeleine Pioche de La Vergne), 1634-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12636</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12333714</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12333714</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59724</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59724)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 189:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The princess of Monpensier written originally in French, and now newly rendered into English.</title>
                  <title>Princesse de Monpensier. English</title>
                  <author>La Fayette, Madame de (Marie-Madeleine Pioche de La Vergne), 1634-1693.</author>
                  <author>Segrais, Jean Regnauld de, 1624-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 83 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Princesse de Monpensier.</note>
                  <note>Written by Madame de La Fayette. Jean Regnauld de Segrais also erroneously cited as joint author. Cf. BM; NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>First English ed. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59724:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59724:1"/>
            <p>THE PRINCESS OF Monpenſier.</p>
            <p>Written Originally in French, and now newly rendered into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59724:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59724:2"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough generally all Tranſlations merit an excuſe, and though I am not ſo much a ſtranger to my
<pb facs="tcp:59724:3"/>own inabilities, and to the modern Mode of Writing, as to be ignorant, how requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite it is for me to make an Apology for my ſelf, and to beg Pardon for this attempt; yet I ſhall at preſent take the liberty upon me, neither to perform the one, nor the other: ſince, if good, the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation deſerves no excuſe; and if bad, it merits no Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. I ſhall only inform the Reader, that this Tranſlation is owing to ſome vacant
<pb facs="tcp:59724:3"/>hours, and to a Friends re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, who having commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Book to me, &amp; deſiring me to tranſlate it, I confeſs at firſt (through the ſmall eſteem which I have ever had for Romances, ſince I underſtood better Books) I made ſome difficulty to grant his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt; But being informed (though the French Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, out of his reſpect to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons deſcended from thoſe mentioned in this Relation, endeavours to perſwade us to
<pb facs="tcp:59724:4"/>the contrary) that this Story was real, and no fiction; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved at length to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to his deſire, and to adventure upon the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Book, which I heard had received ſuch general commendations; how deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly (ſince Mens fancies are ſo different) I ſhall not take upon me to determine, but ſhall leave that, together with the Tranſlation, to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther approved of, or condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by the judicious Reader.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="bookseller_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59724:4"/>
            <head>THE French Bookſeller TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE reſpect which we owe to the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Name which this Book bears for its Title, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
<pb facs="tcp:59724:5"/>which we ought to have for the Eminent Perſons which are deſcended from them who have born it, obliges me to ſay (not to fail of reſpect either to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the one, or the other) that it has not been taken from any Manuſcript which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining to us of the Time wherein thoſe Perſons herein mention'd Liv'd: The Author being willing only for his diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to write Adventures, invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:59724:5"/>to pleaſe his fancy, has judged it more proper to take names known in our Hiſtories, then to make uſe of thoſe which are found in Romances; believing that the Reputation of the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> would not be at all blemiſhed by a relation which in effect is fabulous. If this be not his opinion, I have endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make an amends for it by this Advertiſement, which will prove as advantageous to the
<pb facs="tcp:59724:6"/>Author, as it will appear re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfull from me, both towards the Dead, who are intereſſed in it, and towards the Living whom it may concern.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59724:6"/>
            <head>THE PRINCESS OF Monpenſier.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hil'ſt the Rage and fury of a Civil War (during the reign of <hi>Charls</hi> the ninth) rent <hi>France</hi> in pieces, Love was not wanting to find room amidſt thoſe diſorders; and to cauſe as great in his own Empire, as the Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59724:7"/>and ſelf-ends of ſome Great Ones cauſed in that Dominion.</p>
            <p>The only Daughter of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Mezieres,</hi> an Heireſs very conſiderable, no leſs for her great Eſtate, then for her alliance to the Illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Anjou,</hi> from whence ſhe was deſcended; was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in marriage to the Duke of <hi>Maine,</hi> a younger Brother to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (ſince called <hi>Balafre.</hi>) The only want of years in this great Heireſs ſeem'd to retard her marriage: during which time the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who ſaw her often, diſcovering in her the early appearances of a Beauty (which age in a ſhort time was like to render moſt accompliſh'd) grew ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding amorous of her, and fortune prov'd ſo favourable to him that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a reciprocal return of his affection.</p>
            <p>They long (with care) conceal'd their Love, the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (who was not then poſſeſt with ſo much ambition, as ſince) ardently wiſhed to marry her; but the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59724:7"/>fear to diſpleaſe the Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who ſerved him inſtead of a Father, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him from declaring his intentions.</p>
            <p>In this condition were affairs, when as the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> who could not but with envy behold the riſe of that of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> perceiving the advantage which they would receive by this marriage, reſolved to deprive them of it, and to make it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to themſelves, in procuring this Heireſs to marry the young Prince of <hi>Monpenſier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Endeavours were uſed to execute this deſign with ſuch ſucceſs, that the friends of <hi>Madamoiſelle de Mezieres,</hi> contrary to the promiſes which they had made to the Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> reſolved to beſtow her in marriage on that young Prince. The whole houſe of <hi>Guiſe</hi> were extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurpriz'd at their proceedings, but the Duke, above the reſt, ſeemed to be ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd with grief; the intereſt of his Love made him receive this breach of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59724:8"/>their word as an unſufferable affront; and in ſpight of all the perſwaſions and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to the contrary (by the Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Aumale,</hi> his Uncles, who would not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear too obſtinate in a buſineſs which they perceived beyond their power to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) his reſentment ſoon appear'd, and with ſuch violence too in the very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> that from thence proceeded a hatred between them, which finiſhed not, but with their Lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madamoiſelle de Mezieres,</hi> importun'd by her Relations to marry that Prince, and perceiving otherwiſe that 'twas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for her to marry the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> beſides her vertue prompting her, that 'twas dangerous to have that Perſon for a Brother-in-Law, whom ſhe had wiſhed for as a Husband, in the end reſolv'd to follow the inclination of her friends, and conjur'd the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> no longer, by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59724:8"/>any new obſtacle to divert their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
            <p>In fine ſhe married the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſier,</hi> who ſhortly after carried her to <hi>Champigni</hi> (the uſual ſeat belonging to the Princes of his family) withdrawing her from <hi>Paris,</hi> where the burthen of the war was like to fall heavieſt; that great City being menac'd to ſuſtain a ſiege from the <hi>Huguenots</hi> Army, of which the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was General, who now for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time had begun to declare War againſt the King.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> even in his childhood had contracted a firm, and particular friendſhip with the Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> who was a man far more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd in years then himſelf, and a perſon of extraordinary merit. This Count had been ſo ſenſible of the eſteem, and of the confidence which this young Prince repoſed in him, that contrary to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements which he had made to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59724:9"/>Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> who gave him hopes of conſiderable imployments in the <hi>Huguenots</hi> party, he declar'd himſelf for the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks; ſince he could not reſolve to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite in any thing to a Perſon, that was ſo dear to him. This alteration of Party having no other known foundation, it was doubted whether it were real or no; and the Queen-Mother, <hi>Catherine de Medicis,</hi> had ſuch great ſuſpitions of him, that the War being declar'd by the <hi>Huguenots,</hi> ſhe had a deſign to arreſt him, and to ſecure his Perſon, had not the Prince of <hi>Monpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier</hi> endeavour'd to hinder it, and carried <hi>Chabanes</hi> to <hi>Champigni,</hi> in company with his Wife.</p>
            <p>The Count being of a very pleaſant, and very agreeable humour, he ſoon gain'd the eſteem of the Princeſs of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſier,</hi> and in a ſhort time ſhe repos'd no leſs confidence in him, and had no leſs ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for him, then had the Prince her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. <hi>Chabanes</hi> on his ſide beheld with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59724:9"/>admiration ſo much Beauty, Wit, and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; which appear'd in this young Princeſs, and making uſe of the friendſhip which ſhe ſhewed him to inſpire her with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of an extraordinary Vertue, and worthy of the greatneſs of her birth; he in a ſmall time render'd her one of the moſt accompliſh'd Perſons in the world.</p>
            <p>The Prince being return'd to Court, (call'd thither by the continuation of the War) the Count remain'd alone with the Princeſs, and began to have a reſpect, and an amity for her, proportionable both to her quality, and merits. The confidence which they repos'd in each other, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented on both ſides, but grew ſo great on the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſiers</hi> part, that ſhe acquainted him with the inclination and affection which ſhe had had for the Duke of <hi>Guiſe:</hi> but ſhe inform'd him alſo at the ſame inſtant, that her Love was now almoſt extinct, and that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd no more at preſent, then what
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59724:10"/>was requiſite to defend her heart, from any ſuch other inclination; and that her Vertue, joyning it ſelf to the remainder of this impreſſion, ſhe was not capable to have any thing but diſdain and averſion for all thoſe who ſhould dare to have any Love for her.</p>
            <p>The Count, who knew the ſincerity of this fair Princeſs, and who perceiv'd in her, diſpoſitions ſo contrary to be enſnar'd with the inticing baits of gallantry, and courtſhip, doubted not at all of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of her words; Yet notwithſtanding his Reaſon prov'd too weak a defence to protect him from the aſſaulting charms of a Beauty, in whoſe company, 'twas his fortune to be every day, ſo that at length he became paſſionately enamour'd of this Princeſs, and whatſoever ſhame at firſt poſſes'd him to be thus vanquiſh'd, yet in the end he was forc'd to ſubmit, and to affect her with the moſt ſincere, and violent paſſion, which perhaps ever was;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59724:10"/>And though he was not Maſter of his heart, yet he prov'd ſo of his actions. The alteration of his mind chang'd not at all his humour, ſo that none ſuſpected him to be in Love.</p>
            <p>He took great care, during the ſpace of a whole year, to hide it from the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and he believ'd that he ſhould alwayes have had the ſame deſire to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd it from her. But Love produc'd the ſame effects in him which it generally does in all Lovers, cauſing in him a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to reveal his affection, and after all thoſe difficulties which are wont to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex Lovers on the like occaſions, he at laſt took on him the boldneſs to acquaint her with his affection, being before well prepar'd to endure the violence of that ſtorm, wherewith the haughty humour of this Princeſs ſeem'd to menace him. But he found in her a tranquillity, and a coldneſs worſe a thouſand times then all the rigour, and ill uſage, which he had expected.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:59724:11"/>
            <p>She took not ſo much pains, to put her ſelf in a Paſſion for what he had ſay'd; ſhe only in few words repreſented to him the difference between their Qualities, and Age, the particular knowledge which he had of her vertue, and of the inclination which ſhe had had for the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> but, above the reſt, what he ow'd to the friendſhip of the Prince her Husband, and to the confidence which he repos'd in him. The Count (at theſe words) thought he ſhould have dyed at her feet, through ſhame and grief; but ſhe indeavour'd to comfort him in aſſuring him, that ſhe would never remember what he had told her, and that ſhe would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be perſwaded to believe a thing which was ſo diſadvantageous to him, and that ſhe would ever ſtill regard him, as her beſt friend.</p>
            <p>Theſe aſſurances (as may be imagin'd) were ſome conſolation to the Count; but yet he made a ſenſible diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59724:11"/>of the diſdain, and averſion, which the Princeſs had for him through her words; and the next day, though he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held her with a countenance as uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd as formerly, yet his grief and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction much increas'd. The Princeſs on her part leſſen'd not at all the eſteem which ſhe before had for him, ſhe us'd him with the ſame affability as ſhe was accuſtom'd to do: and often (when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſerv'd) took an opportunity to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the inclination which ſhe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had for the Duke of <hi>Guiſe:</hi> and Fame beginning then to publiſh to the world thoſe great and excellent qualities which appear'd in that Prince, ſhe confeſs'd to him that ſhe was extream glad to hear it, and that ſhe much rejoyc'd to find that he merited the affection which ſhe had had for him.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſigns of confidence, which had been formerly ſo dear to the Count, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came now inſupportable to him; yet he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59724:12"/>durſt not ſhew his diſpleaſure to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, though ſometimes he preſum'd to put her in mind of that which he had had the boldneſs to declare to her.</p>
            <p>After two years of abſence (Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made) the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd home to viſit the Princeſs his Wife, cover'd o're with the Lawrels, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which he had gain'd at the ſiege of <hi>Paris,</hi> and at the Battel of St. <hi>Dennis.</hi> He was ſurpriz'd to find the Beauty of this Princeſs arriv'd to ſo great a perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and through an inclination of Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie (which was natural to him) he ſeem'd to be troubl'd at it; foreſeeing well, that he ſhould not be the only Perſon, to whom ſhe would appear fair. He much rejoyc'd to ſee the Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> for whom his kindneſs was not at all dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd: he demanded earneſtly of him a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the humour, and conditions of his Wife, who appear'd almoſt a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to him through the ſmall ſpace of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59724:12"/>time which he had liv'd with her.</p>
            <p>The Count with a ſincereneſs, as exact, as if he had not been at all in Love, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd to the Prince all what he knew of this Princeſs capable to make him Love her; and he alſo advertiz'd the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> of all things which ſhe ought to perform fully to gain the heart and eſtimation of her Husband.</p>
            <p>In fine, the Counts Paſſion ſo naturally inclin'd him to think of nothing elſe, but what might augment the proſperity, and happineſs of this Princeſs, that he ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily forgot how much it concerns Lovers to hinder Perſons they are in Love with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, from keeping a perfect correſpondence with their Husbands.</p>
            <p>Scarce was the Peace concluded, but the War began to be renew'd again, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd by the deſign which the King had to arreſt at <hi>Noiers</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> and the Admiral of <hi>Chaſtillon;</hi> and this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign having been diſcover'd, they began
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59724:13"/>on both ſides to make new preparations for War, which conſtrain'd the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> to leave his Wife, and to make his appearance there, where both his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and his duty call'd him. <hi>Chabanes</hi> follow'd him to Court, having fully juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied himſelf in the Queens opinion. It was not without extream grief that he depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Princeſs, who on her ſide re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd much perplext with the thoughts of thoſe dangers which her Husband was going to expoſe himſelf to, in the War.</p>
            <p>The Chiefs of the <hi>Huguenots</hi> party re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring themſelves to <hi>Rochel, Poictu,</hi> and <hi>Xaintonge</hi> being on their ſide, the War grew hot, and the King aſſembl'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all his forces to ſuppreſs their Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. The Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> his Brother (who was ſince ſtil'd <hi>Henry</hi> the Third) acquir'd much honour by ſeveral gallant actions which he perform'd, and amongſt the reſt at the Battel of <hi>Jarnac,</hi> where the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was kil'd. In this War,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59724:13"/>it was that the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> began firſt to have conſiderable imployments, and to make it appear that he ſurpaſs'd by much the great hopes which had been conceiv'd of him.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> who hated him, both as his particular enemy, and as that of his Family, beheld with Jealous eyes the Glory of the Duke, as well as the kindneſs which the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> ſhew'd him.</p>
            <p>After that both Armies had tir'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by ſeveral ſmall encounters; by a common conſent of both Parties, the Troops were licenc'd for ſome time, to retire to their ſeveral Garriſons. The Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> remain'd at <hi>Loches</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute orders to all thoſe places which in probability were like to be attacq'd by the Enemy; the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> tarried with him, and the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> accompanied with the Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> return'd to <hi>Champigni,</hi> which was not far diſtant from thence.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59724:14"/>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> went often to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the Places which he was about to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, and one day as he return'd to <hi>Loches</hi> by a by-way unknown to thoſe of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who bragg'd that he knew it, plac'd himſelf at the head of the Troop to ſerve them inſtead of a Guide; but after that he had rid ſome time, he loſt himſelf, and found that he was upon the bank of a ſmall River, which was unknown to him. The Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> rallied with him, and jear'd him for his ill conduct, and making a ſtop there (being diſpos'd to mirth, as uſually young Princes are) they perceiv'd a ſmall Boat which ſtood ſtill in the midſt of the River, which not being very broad, they could eaſily diſtinguiſh objects, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in the Boat three or four Women, and amongſt the reſt, one who appear'd to them very fair, who was in rich apparel, and who attentively regarded two men, who were in the ſame Boat with her, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59724:14"/>were a fiſhing. This adventure caus'd a new joy both to theſe young Princes, and to thoſe of their Train. It appear'd to them as a Romance-like accident, ſome telling the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> that he had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely loſt them only to make them have a view of this fair Perſon, others ſaying that (after what Fortune had done for him) he muſt of neceſſity grow amorous of her; and the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, that he was oblig'd to become her Lover.</p>
            <p>In fine, being reſolv'd to ſee the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of this adventure, they caus'd ſome of their followers to ride into the River, as far as poſſible, and to call to that La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and tell her, that the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> was there, and that he would willingly croſs the Water, and intreated her to come, and take him in. This Lady (who was the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi>) hearing it ſay'd that the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> was there, and not doubting at all (through the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59724:15"/>quantity of people which ſhe ſaw on the Rivers-ſide) but that it was he, caus'd her Boat to advance towards that ſide of the River, where he was; His graceful Mine made her ſoon diſtinguiſh him from the reſt, but yet ſhe ſooner took notice of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> whoſe ſight wrought in her ſuch an alteration that it caus'd her to bluſh, which rather aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, then decreas'd her Beauty, and made her appear to the Eyes of theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as a Perſon ſupernatural, and wholly divine.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (in ſpight of that advantageous alteration which two or three years, ſince laſt he ſaw her, had made in her) immediately knew her, and inform'd the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> who ſhe was, who was at firſt aſham'd of the Liberty which he had taken, but perceiving the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> ſo fair, and this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture ſo much pleaſing him, he reſolv'd to compleat it, and after a thouſand ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59724:15"/>and a thouſand complements, he invented a ſtory of ſome conſiderable bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, which he ſay'd he had to do on the other ſide of the River, and accepted of the proffer which ſhe made him to carry him over in her Boat; he enter'd it alone acompanied only with the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> giving order to thoſe that follow'd them to go, and croſs the River at ſome other place, and to come and meet him at <hi>Champigni,</hi> which the Princeſs inform'd them was not above two Leagues diſtant from thence.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as they were in the Boat, the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> inquir'd of her, to what propitious Fate it was they ow'd ſo fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate an adventure; and what detain'd her there in the midſt of the River. She an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd him, That ſhe came from <hi>Champigni</hi> in company with the Prince her Husband, with a deſign to hunt; but finding her ſelf too much tir'd, ſhe came for refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Rivers ſide; where the curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59724:16"/>to ſee a Salmon taken (which had entangl'd it ſelf in a Net) had caus'd her to enter the Boat. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> did not at all intereſt himſelf in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but feeling that Paſſion began to revive again in his breaſt, which he had formerly had for that Princeſs, he ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that he ſhould find it a difficult task to eſcape from this adventure, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming again her captive.</p>
            <p>They ſoon arriv'd to the other ſide of the River, where they found the Pages, and Servants of the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> who there attended her. The Dukes of <hi>Anjou</hi> and <hi>Guiſe</hi> aſſiſted her to get on Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, where ſhe comported her ſelf with an admirable grace. During the way, ſhe entertain'd them with moſt exquiſite diſcourſe upon ſeveral ſubjects; ſo that they were no leſs ſurpriz'd and charm'd with her excellent parts, then they had been before with her Beauty, and they could not forbear to acquaint her how
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59724:16"/>extreamly they were amaz'd with thoſe extraordinary perfections which they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd in her. She anſwer'd to thoſe commendations which they gave her with all the modeſty imaginable, but a little more coldly to thoſe which came from Duke of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> being willing to uſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'dneſs towards him, which ſhould hinder him from building any hopes upon the inclination which formerly ſhe had for him.</p>
            <p>Arriving at the outward-moſt Court at <hi>Champigni,</hi> they found the Prince of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſier,</hi> who but then return'd from hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. His amazement was great to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold two men ride on each ſide of his Wife, but it augmented extreamly, when (approaching nearer) he perceiv'd that they were, the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> The hatred which he had for the laſt, joyning it ſelf to his natural jealouſie made him find ſomething ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant to him to ſee theſe Princes in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59724:17"/>company with his Wife, without knowing what accident had brought them together, nor what they came to do at his houſe, that he could not conceal the diſorder which it caus'd in him, though cunningly he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the cauſe of it upon the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which he had, that he ſhould not be able to receive ſo great a Prince, both according to his quality and to his own wiſhes.</p>
            <p>The Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> appear'd yet more perplext to ſee the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> with the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> than ſeem'd the Prince himſelf. The adventure which Fortune had made uſe of to bring theſe two Perſons together appear'd to him as an unlucky Omen, from whence he prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticated that this Romance-like begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning would be follow'd by other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of the like nature.</p>
            <p>At Night the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd theſe Princes very generouſly, and with a civility which was natural to her.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59724:17"/>In fine, ſhe pleas'd her Gueſts but too well. The Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> who was a Prince of a comely perſonage, and very accompliſh'd, could not behold a perſon ſo worthy of him, without ardently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to enjoy her; ſoon became infected with the ſame Diſeaſe which poſſeſt the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and alwayes feigning ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary affairs, he remain'd two dayes at <hi>Champigni,</hi> without being oblig'd to ſtay by any other motive, then by the charms of the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier;</hi> the Prince her Husband not uſing any intreaties to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him there.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> before he departed, took an opportunity to acquaint the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, that he was ſtill the ſame, which he had ever been, (and ſince his Paſſion had never been reveal'd to any) he often told her in publick (without being over-heard by any, but her ſelf) that there was no change in his affection, but that at preſent
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59724:18"/>he retain'd as much adoration, and reſpect for her, as ever.</p>
            <p>In fine, the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and he at length departed from <hi>Champigni</hi> with much regret. They rid a long while with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeaking one to the other, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd in a profound ſilence, till at laſt the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> imagining that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps their ſilence might proceed from one and the ſame cauſe, demanded briskly of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> if he meditated upon the beauty, and perfections of the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier.</hi> This brisk demand, joyn'd to what the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> had already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, concerning the inclinations of the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> made him perceive, that infallibly he would become his Rival, and that it extreamly imported him, not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his Love to that Prince; but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of all ſuſpition, he anſwer'd him ſmiling; That he appear'd himſelf ſo much taken up with the imagination,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59724:18"/>wherewith he accus'd him, that he had judg'd it uncivil to interrupt him; That the Beauty of the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> was no new thing to him; That he had accuſtom'd himſelf to gaze on the Luſter of her charms, without being dazel'd with them, ever ſince ſhe was deſign'd to have been his Siſter-in-Law, but that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd very well, that all perſons were not ſo well prepar'd againſt them as himſelf. The Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> ingeniouſly confeſt to him, that he had neyer yet ſeen any thing, which in his opinion, ſeem'd comparable to this young Princeſs; and that he found very well, that her preſence might prove dangerous to him, if he ſhould often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf in her company: he would fain have made the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> confeſs, that he apprehended the ſame Fate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf too: but the Duke (who began now to make a ſerious affair of his Love) would confeſs nothing to him.</p>
            <p>Theſe Princes returning to <hi>Loches</hi> enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59724:19"/>themſelves often with a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing diſcourſe of the adventure which had caus'd them to diſcover the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier:</hi> but it prov'd not a ſubject of ſo great diverſion at <hi>Champigni.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> was diſcontented at all which had happen'd, without being able to give a Reaſon wherefore. His Wifes being in the Boat, appear'd to him as an unlucky accident: It ſeem'd to him, that ſhe had entertain'd theſe Princes too kindly; and that which diſpleas'd him moſt, was to have obſerv'd that the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> had regarded her very atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</p>
            <p>Theſe thoughts caus'd him from that inſtant, to conceive a furious jealouſie, which made him to remember the paſſion, and reſentment, which that Duke had ſhewn againſt his Marriage, and he had ſome thoughts, that, from that very time he had been amorous of her. The ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour which theſe ſuſpitions put him into,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59724:19"/>caus'd ſometimes but ill uſage to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Monpenſier.</hi> The Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> (according to his cuſtome) took care to hinder, that their private diſcontents, broke not out into an open quarrel, endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring through that, to perſwade the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs how great, and real the paſſion was, which he had for her, and how diſintereſs'd from all ſelf-ends.</p>
            <p>Yet he could not refrain from asking her the effect which the ſight of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> had produc'd in her. She acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, That ſhe had been troubl'd at it, through the ſhame which ſhe had, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the kindneſs which ſhe had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſhew'd him: ſhe confeſt that ſhe had found him far more accompliſh't now, then at that time; and that his diſcourſe ſeem'd to intimate, that he would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her to believe, that he ſtill affected her; but ſhe aſſur'd him, that nothing was able to force her to relinquiſh the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which ſhe had taken never to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59724:20"/>engage her ſelf in ſo perilous an Affair.</p>
            <p>The Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> was much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyc'd to hear this reſolution; but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could ſecure him againſt the ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he had of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> He repreſented to the Princeſs, that he extreamly fear'd, that the firſt impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of her Love would ſoon return, and made her apprehend the mortal grief which (for their common intreſt) he ſhould have, if one day he ſhould ſee her change her preſent reſolutions. The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> (alwayes continuing her reſerv'dneſs towards him) ſcarce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd to what he ſaid concerning his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and never conſider'd him, but in the Quality of her faithful'ſt friend, without doing him the honour to take notice of him as her Lover.</p>
            <p>The Armies having quitted their Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and being again upon their march, the Princes return'd to their ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> found
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59724:20"/>it convenient, that his Wife ſhould come to <hi>Paris,</hi> to be no more ſo near thoſe places which were the ſeat of the War. The <hi>Huguenots</hi> beſieg'd the City of <hi>Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiers,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> caſt himſelf in the Town to defend it, where he perform'd ſuch actions, during the Siege, which alone were ſufficient to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for ever famous any other perſon, but himſelf.</p>
            <p>Soon after, was fought the Battel of <hi>Moncontour,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had taken St. <hi>John d' Angely,</hi> fell ſick, and immediately quitted the Army, either through the violence of his diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or through the deſire which he had to return and take his eaſe, and to partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of the pleaſures and recreations en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd at <hi>Paris,</hi> where the preſence of the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> was not the leaſt attracting object that drew him thither.</p>
            <p>The Army continued under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59724:21"/>ſoon after, Peace being concluded, the Court, return'd to <hi>Paris</hi> where the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Princeſs eclips'd the Luſter of all thoſe, who till then had been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd; and the charming perfections both of her Wit and Perſon ſoon attracted the eyes of all the Court upon her, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd her as a perſon that ſurpaſs'd hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity. The Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> chang'd not at all, at <hi>Paris,</hi> the inclinations which he had conceiv'd for her at <hi>Champigni;</hi> and he took an extream care to acquaint her with as much through all his actions, taking notwithſtanding great heed not to render her too apparent teſtimonies of his affection, through fear to give jealouſie to the Prince her Husband.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> was now become paſſionately inamour'd of this Princeſs, and being willing (for ſeveral reaſons) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal his paſſion, he reſolv'd with the firſt opportunity to declare it privately to her, thereby to avoy'd all thoſe various re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59724:21"/>which generally ſprings from pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Courtſhip. Being one day at the Queens appartment at a time when there was ſmall company there (the Queen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing retir'd to diſcourſe about buſineſs with the Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain</hi>) the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> coming in, he reſolv'd to make uſe of that opportunity which Fortune preſented him with, to ſpeak to her; and approaching to her, I go about to ſurpriſe you Madam, (ſaid he) and to diſpleaſe you, in acquainting you, that I have ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd and cheriſh'd that paſſion which formerly was not unknown to you, but which ſince (through again ſeeing of you) is ſo much augmented, that neither the ſeverity nor hatred of the Prince your Husband, nor the Pretenſions, and Rival<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the firſt Prince of the Realm, are able to reprieve me one moment from its violence. It would indeed have ſhew'd more reſpectful from me, to have reveal'd it to you by my actions; but Madam, my
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59724:22"/>actions had diſcover'd it to others, as well as to your ſelf; and I only deſire, that you alone ſhould know, that I am ſo preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptious to adore you.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs was at firſt ſo ſurpriz'd with this diſcourſe, that ſhe had no power to interrupt him; but recollecting her ſelf, and going about to anſwer him, the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> enter'd the Room, whoſe preſence, with what the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> had ſaid to her, ſo diſorder'd and perplext the Princeſs, that it poſſes'd him with greater ſuſpitions, then if he had over-heard the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi>'s diſcourſe. The Queen came out of her Cloſet, and the Duke retir'd himſelf, to cure the Prince of jealouſie.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> at night found her Husband poſſeſt with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt melancholly imaginable, and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hav'd himſelf ſo paſſionately towards her, that he forbid her evermore to ſpeak to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> which caus'd her to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59724:22"/>to her appartment; much poſſeſt with ſadneſs, for the adventures which had happen'd to her that day.</p>
            <p>The next following, ſhe ſaw the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> at the Queens Lodgings; but he kept at a diſtance, and came not near her, but contented himſelf to go out of the Room preſently after her, to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to her, that he had no buſineſs there, when ſhe was abſent.</p>
            <p>Scarce a day paſt in which ſhe did not receive a thouſand conceal'd aſſurances of this Dukes paſſion, without that he ever ſo much as attempted to mention it to her, but at ſuch a time when none could take notice of it, and as ſhe was well aſſur'd of the reallity of this paſſion, ſhe began (notwithſtanding all the reſolutions which ſhe had made at <hi>Champigni</hi> to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) to feel ſomething of that paſſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn in her heart, which had formerly poſſeſt it.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> on his part forgot
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59724:23"/>nothing which might declare his Love to her in all places where 'twas his fortune to ſee her, and made it his buſineſs conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to follow her, when ſhe rendred viſits to the Queen his Mother.</p>
            <p>About this time, it was taken notice of, that the Princeſs <hi>Margaret</hi> his Siſter (who much affected him, and who was ſince Queen of <hi>Navarr</hi>) had ſome kindneſs for the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and that which diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd it more, was, the reſervedneſs which the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> ſhew'd to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> The Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> ſoon learn't this news, which ſeem'd not indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to her, and which made her more ſenſible of the concern which ſhe had for the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> then ſhe thought ſhe had been. <hi>Monſieur de Monpenſier</hi> (her Father-in-Law) then marrying <hi>Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Guiſe</hi> (Siſter to that Duke) ſhe was conſtrain'd to ſee him often in thoſe places, where the preſence of both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties was requiſite to celebrate the Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Ceremonies.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:59724:23"/>
            <p>The Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> no longer able to endure a man for her Servant, whom all <hi>France</hi> believ'd in Love with the Princeſs <hi>Margaret,</hi> reſolv'd to take on her the boldneſs to acquaint him, how much ſhe thought her ſelf injur'd. And being offended, and griev'd that ſhe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd her ſelf, One day, as the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> met her at his Siſters, being ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from other company, and being about to ſpeak to her concerning his paſſion, ſhe briskly interrupted him, with a tone that ſignified her diſpleaſure, and replyed, I cannot comprehend why you ſhould build ſuch hopes upon the weak foundation of a folly, which I was guilty of at thirteen years old, as that you ſhould have the boldneſs at preſent to make Love to ſuch a perſon as my ſelf, but above all, at ſuch a time, when in the view of the whole Court, you appear engag'd to an other.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> that had a great deal of Wit, and was much in Love, had
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59724:24"/>need to conſult with no Oracle to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the meaning of the Princeſſes words, anſwer'd her with much reſpect; <hi>I confeſs</hi> Madam, <hi>that I have been too blame, not to deſpiſe the honour of being Brother-in-law to my King, rather then to let you ſuſpect one moment, that I could deſire to poſſeſs any other heart, then yours; but if you will do me the favour as to hear me, I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent I ſhall juſtifie my ſelf in your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> reply'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but ſhe remain'd ſtill, and went not away from him, and the Duke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that ſhe granted him the audience, which he had demanded, and wiſh'd for; acquainted her, That, without any endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of his own, us'd to gain it, the Princeſs <hi>Margaret</hi> had honour'd him with her affection; but that having no Love for her, <q>He had but very ill recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penc'd the favour which ſhe did him, untill ſuch time that ſhe had giv'n him
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59724:24"/>ſome hopes to marry her; that in truth, the grandure to which this match might raiſe him, had oblig'd him to render her more obſervance and reſpect, then uſuall, which it ſeem'd had giv'n cauſe of ſuſpition both to the King, and to the Duke of <hi>Anjou;</hi> That the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition both of the one, and the other diſſwaded him not from his deſign; but if that deſign diſpleas'd her, he would from that very inſtant abandon it, and never think on it more, during his Life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This oblation which the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> made of his own intr'eſt to pleaſe the Princeſs, ſoon made her forget all the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, and diſpleaſure wherewith ſhe had entertain'd him, when he firſt began to ſpeak to her. She ſoon chang'd her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and began to entertain him with the weakneſs which poſſeſt the Princeſs <hi>Margaret</hi> to Love him firſt, and of the conſiderable advantage which he would
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59724:25"/>receive in marrying her. In concluſion, without ſaying any thing obliging to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> ſhe diſcovered to him a thouſand charming perfections, which he had formerly ador'd in <hi>Madamoiſelle de Meziens:</hi> and though they had not long diſcours'd together, yet they found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo accuſtom'd to one anothers hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, that Love which was no ſtranger to their breaſts, ſoon found out a way to return again into its ancient Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel.</p>
            <p>They thus finiſh'd this agreeable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, which left a very ſenſible im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Joy upon the Duke of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> nor did the Princeſs participate a leſs ſhare than he, to learn that he yet really affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted her. But when ſhe was retir'd to her Cloſet, what reflections did ſhe not make upon the ſhame which ſhe had, in ſuffering her ſelf to be ſo ſoon or'ecome by the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi>'s excuſes; upon that Labyrinth of trouble, which ſhe was ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59724:25"/>about to involve her ſelf into, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging her ſelf in a buſineſs, which ſhe had regarded with ſo much horrour, and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, and upon the diſmal misfortunes, wherewith the jealous humour of her Husband ſeem'd to threaten her, but theſe unpleaſant thoughts were the next day ſoon diſcipated by the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi>'s preſence.</p>
            <p>He fail'd not to render her an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of that which paſt between the Princeſs <hi>Margaret</hi> and himſelf, the new alliance of their Houſes, often preſented him with opportunities to ſpeak to her; but he had no ſmall trouble to cure her of the jealouſie which the Beauty of the Princeſs <hi>Margaret</hi> gave her, againſt which all his Vows were to weak to ſecure her from ſuſpition. This jealouſie ſerv'd the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> to defend the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of her heart, againſt the endeavours us'd to gain it by the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who already poſſeſt its greateſt part.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:59724:26"/>
            <p>The Kings marriage with the Princeſs <hi>Iſabella</hi> (Daughter to the Emperour <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximilian</hi>) fil'd the whole Court with feaſts and rejoycings. The King gave a Ball, where the Princeſs <hi>Margaret,</hi> and the reſt of the Princeſſes danc't, the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> appearing the only perſon that could diſpute the prize of Beauty with her. The Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and four others, which were of their company danc'd an Antick-dance in the ſhape of <hi>Moors,</hi> their Habits were all alike, and ſuch as are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally us'd on the like occaſion.</p>
            <p>The firſt time that the Ball was danc'd, the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> before he danc'd (not having put on his vizard) ſay'd ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in paſſing by to the Princeſs of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſier,</hi> ſhe ſoon perceiv'd that the Prince her Husband had taken notice of it, which much diſturb'd her. Soon after ſeeing the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> with his Vizard on, and dreſt like a Moor, coming to ſpeak to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59724:26"/>her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> perplex'd through her diſorder, ſhe believ'd that it was ſtill the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and approaching to him, Have no reſpect too night (ſaid ſhe) but for the Princeſs <hi>Margaret.</hi> I ſhall not be jealous, 'tis my command, I am obſerv'd, approach me no more. As ſoon as ſhe had finiſh'd theſe words, ſhe retir'd, and the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> remain'd as ſurpriz'd, as if he had been Thunder-ſtruck, he perceiv'd at that inſtant that he had not only a Rival, but a Rival too belov'd; he ſoon apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the name of the Princeſs <hi>Margaret,</hi> that that Rival was the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and he made no queſtion, but that the Princeſs his Siſter was the oblation which had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> favourable to the vows of his Rival.</p>
            <p>Jealouſie, Deſpight and Rage joyning themſelves to the hatred, which he had already for him, caus'd him to be poſſeſt with whatſoever may be imagin'd of a moſt violent, and impetuous paſſion, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59724:27"/>which had immediately produc'd ſome bloody Effect of his diſpleaſure, had not that diſſimulation which was ſo natural to him (and which at preſent was ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite) ſoon reſcu'd his Reaſon, from thoſe violent motions of his paſſion, and oblig'd him, for ſeveral prevalent reaſons, (as affairs then ſtood) not to attempt any thing againſt the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> Yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs he could not deprive himſelf of the ſatisfaction which he took to tell him, that he knew the ſecret of his Love; and accoſting him in going out of the Room where they had danc'd, 'Tis too much (ſaid he) to dare at once to raiſe your ambitious thoughts, to pretend to my Siſter, and to deprive me of my Miſtris. The reſpect which I bear the King, hinders me at preſent, from declaring my reſentment; But remember that perhaps the loſs of your life, ſhall be the ſmalleſt puniſhment where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, ſome time or other I ſhall chaſtize your temerity. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:59724:27"/>though unaccuſtom'd to ſuch menaces, yet he had no opportunity left him for an anſwer, becauſe the King who went out at that inſtant, call'd them both, to ſpeak to them, but they imprinted in his heart a deſire of revenge, which he endeavour'd all his life time to ſatisfie.</p>
            <p>From that very Night the Duke of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jou</hi> began to render him all ſort of ill turns (that lay in his pow'r) with the King: he perſwaded him that the Princeſs his Siſter would never conſent to marry the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> (with whom it was then propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to marry her) ſo long as the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> was ſuffer'd to come near her, and that it was a ſhame to ſuffer that one of his ſubjects (to ſatisfie his own Ambition) ſhould bring any obſtacle to a buſineſs, which (in probability) might give peace to <hi>France.</hi> The King bore already ill will enough againſt the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and this diſcourſe ſo augmented it, that ſeeing him next day, as he was about to enter
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59724:28"/>the Room, deſign'd for the Ball, at the Queens Lodgings (adorn'd with an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of Jewels, but yet more adorn'd by this graceful mine) he plac'd himſelf before the entrance of the door, and tartly demanded of him, where he went. The Duke without being daunted, anſwer'd, That he came to wait on him (and as it was his duty,) to render him his moſt humble ſervice; to which the King reply'd, that he had no need of it, and ſo turn'd from him, without taking any further notice of him.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> though for all this, did not forbear to enter the Room, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd in his heart both againſt the King and the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> but his grief ſerv'd but to augment his natural fierceneſs, and through ſpight he oftner approach'd the Princeſs <hi>Margaret,</hi> then he had been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom'd to do, ſince what the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> had ſaid to him concerning the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> hinder'd him from regarding her.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:59724:28"/>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> carefully obſerv'd both one and the other: the countenance of that Princeſs (though ſhe endeavour'd all ſhe could to conceal it) diſcover'd the diſpleaſure which ſhe conceiv'd, when the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> ſpoke to the Princeſs <hi>Margaret.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> who through what ſhe had ſaid to him, when ſhe miſtook him for the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> had perceiv'd that ſhe was jealous, hop'd to cauſe a miſunderſtanding between them, and ſetting himſelf down by her; 'Tis for your intreſt, Madam, more then for my own (ſaid he) that I go about to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you, that the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> merits not that you ſhould make choice of him to my prejudice; let me intreat you not to interrupt me to tell me the contrary of a truth, which I but too well know. He deceives you Madam, he ſacrifices you to my Siſter, as he has made an oblation of her, to you. 'Tis a man that is only ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Ambition, but ſince he has had
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59724:29"/>the good fortune to pleaſe you, 'tis enough. I will not hinder him to enjoy a happineſs, which without doubt I merited better then he: I ſhould render my ſelf unworthy of it, if I ſhould ſtrive longer to obtain the conqueſt of a heart, which another poſſeſſes, 'tis enough that I have not hitherto, but incurr'd your diſlike, and I would not willingly cauſe hatred to ſucceed, by any longer importuning you with the moſt ardent, and faithful paſſion that ever was.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> who was very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly wounded both with Love and grief, had ſcarce power to finiſh theſe words, and though he had begun his diſcourſe through a malitious intent, and through a deſire of vengeance; yet he grew ſo mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified in conſidering the Princeſſes Beauty, and the loſs which he receiv'd in looſing the hopes of ever being belov'd, that without attending her anſwer, he went out from the Ball, feigning that he found
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59724:29"/>himſelf indiſpos'd, and went home to his own appartment to muze ſeriouſly upon his misfortune.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> remain'd af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and perplext, as may be eaſily ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd, to ſee her reputation, and her moſt important ſecret, remaining in the hands of a Prince, whom ſhe had treated ill, and and to learn from him (what ſhe could now no longer doubt off) that ſhe had been deceiv'd by her Lover. Which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded together, prov'd things that did not leave her ſo much Miſtris of her paſſions, as was requiſite ſhe ſhould be, in a place deſtin'd only to mirth and jollity, Yet ſhe was forc'd to remain there, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to go and ſup at the Dutcheſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi>'s (her Mother-in-laws) who took her along with her.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> who languiſh'd with impatience to relate to her what the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> had ſaid to him the day before, follow'd her to his Siſters, but
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59724:30"/>how great was his amazement, when go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to entertain this fair Princeſs with diſcourſe, he found that ſhe reply'd not to what he ſaid, but only made him moſt fearful reproaches; and her paſſion caus'd her to make thoſe reproaches ſo confus'dly, that he could comprehend nothing from them, but only that ſhe accus'd him of infidelity and Treaſon.</p>
            <p>Orewhelm'd with deſpair to find cauſe for ſo great an augmentation of grief, where he had hop'd to find conſolation for all his diſcontents; and affecting the Princeſs with a paſſion ſo violent, which left him not that liberty to remain du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious, whither he were again belov'd, or no; he reſolv'd to hazard all at once and to give her an infallible proof of his his affection. You ſhall be ſatisfied Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam (ſaid he) I will do that for you, which all the Royal-Authority ſhould not have obtain'd from me, nor have forc'd me to perform. It will coſt me my Fortune, but
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59724:30"/>that is a thing too inconſiderable to be vallu'd, to ſatisfie you.</p>
            <p>Without remaining any longer at the Dutcheſs his Siſters, he went immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to find out the Cardinals his Unkles, and under pretext of the ill treatment which he had receiv'd from the King, he repreſented to them ſo great a neceſſity, to ſecure his fortune, for him to make it appear, that he had no thoughts to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Princeſs <hi>Margaret,</hi> that he engag'd them to conclude his marriage with the Princeſs of <hi>Portia,</hi> who had already been propounded to him.</p>
            <p>The news of this marriage was ſoon known throughout all <hi>Paris,</hi> every body ſeem'd amaz'd at it, and the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> was poſſes'd at the hearing of it, both with joy, &amp; grief; ſhe was much pleas'd to ſee the power which ſhe had over the Duke of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> but at the ſame inſtant, ſhe was as much diſpleas'd to have caus'd him to relinquiſh a deſign ſo advantageous to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59724:31"/>him, as was his marriage with the Princeſs <hi>Margaret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> who had a mind that Love ſhould recompence him for what he loſt by Fortune, preſt the Princeſs to grant him a private audience, to clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the unjuſt reproaches which ſhe had made him, and he obtain'd from her a promiſe that ſhe would be at the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs of <hi>Monpenſiers</hi> (his Siſters) at ſuch a time when that Dutcheſs ſhould be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and when he might entertain her in private.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> ſoon receiv'd the effect of this promiſe, and had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to proſtrate himſelf at her feet, and the freedome to declare to her his paſſion, and to inform her how much he ſuffer'd through her ſuſpitions. The Princeſs, who could not forget what the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> had told her, (though the Duke of <hi>Guiſes</hi> proceedings ought ſufficiently to have ſecur'd her from jealouſie) acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59724:31"/>him with the juſt cauſe which ſhe had to believe that he had betray'd her, ſince the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> knew that, which it was impoſſible for him to have learnt from any other, but himſelf. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> knew not what defence to make for himſelf, and appear'd as much perplext as the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> to divine who (in probability) had diſcover'd their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence. In fine, in the remainder of her diſcourſe, as ſhe repreſented to him that he had been too blame to precipitate his marriage with the Princeſs of <hi>Portia,</hi> and to abandon that of the Princeſs <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet,</hi> which would have prov'd ſo advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to him, ſhe told him that he might well judge that ſhe was not at all jealouſe of it, ſince that at the Ball ſhe her ſelf had conjur'd him to have no reſpect for any there, but for that Princeſs.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> reply'd, that 'twas poſſible that ſhe might have had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to impoſe that command upon
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59724:32"/>him, but aſſuredly that ſhe had not done it. The Princeſs maintain'd the contrary; and in concluſion, at length with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputing, and examining one an others ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, they found that of neceſſity, ſhe muſt have deceiv'd her ſelf, through the reſemblance of their habits, and that ſhe her ſelf had reveal'd that to the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> which ſhe accus'd the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> to have acquainted him with.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who was almoſt juſtified in her opinion, through his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, became entirely ſo, through this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. This fair Princeſs thought ſhe could not with juſtice refuſe her heart to a man who had formerly poſſeſt it, and who but lately had abandon'd all his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambitious pretenſions for her ſake, ſhe ſoon conſented to accept his ſervices, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him to believe, that ſhe was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of his paſſion. The arrival of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> (her Mother-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law) put a concluſion to this diſcourſe,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59724:32"/>and hinder'd the Duke <hi>Guiſe</hi> from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring to her the tranſports of his joy.</p>
            <p>Shortly after the Court removing to <hi>Bloys,</hi> the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> follow'd it thither, where the marriage of the Princeſs <hi>Margaret,</hi> with the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> was concluded. The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> knowing nothing more of grandure, and good fortune, then to be belov'd by the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> beheld, at preſent, with joy the concluſion of that marriage, which perhaps at another time had o're<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd him with deſpair: but yet he could not ſo well conceal his Love, but that the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> diſcover'd ſomething of it, who being no longer Maſter of his jealouſie, commanded the Princeſs his Wife to depart for <hi>Champigni.</hi> This command ſeem'd very harſh to her, but yet ſhe was forc'd to obey it. She found means to take her leave in private of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> but ſhe was much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex't to find out a ſure way for him to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59724:33"/>convey Letters to her; in fine, after ſhe had ruminated on ſeveral, ſhe at laſt fixt her thoughts upon the Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> who ſhe always accounted for her friend, without conſidering that hewas her Lover.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who knew to what degree the Count was a friend to the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> was amaz'd that ſhe choſe him for her confident: but ſhe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him ſo much of his fidelity, that ſhe ſecur'd him from ſuſpition. This diſcourſe ended, he parted from her poſſeſt with all the grief which abſence and ſeparation (from the belov'd Perſon) can cauſe in the breaſt of an afflicted Lover.</p>
            <p>The Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> who, during the time of the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Blois,</hi> had been ſick at <hi>Paris,</hi> hearing that ſhe went to <hi>Champigni,</hi> met her upon the way, to wait on her thither: She now began to ſhew him ſeveral tokens of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and good will, and teſtified to him an extraordinary impatiency to diſcourſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59724:33"/>with him particularly in private. But what was his ſurprizal and his grief when he found, that this impatiency only ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to relate to him that ſhe was paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately belov'd by the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and that ſhe had a reciprocal kindneſs for him: his grief and his aſtoniſhment was ſo great, that it permitted him not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn a reply to what the Princeſs had ſaid, who was ſo taken up with her paſſion, and who found her mind ſo much eas'd to diſcourſe to him of it, that ſhe took no notice of his ſilence, but went on with her diſcourſe, and related to him what had happen'd to her, with ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs, that ſhe forgot not the leaſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance material to her ſtory. She ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him how the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> and her ſelf were agreed to receive through his means the Letters which they had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd to write to each other.</p>
            <p>Theſe words prov'd like mortal wounds to the Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> to ſee that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59724:34"/>his Miſtris would have him ſerve his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, and that ſhe her ſelf propounded this to him as as a thing which would be very pleaſing to her. Yet he was ſo abſolutely Maſter of himſelf, that he conceal'd from her his reſentment, and only acquainted her how much he was ſurpriz'd to perceive in her ſo great a change. He hop'd at firſt that this alteration of her humour, which depriv'd him of all his hopes, would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of his paſſion too: but he found this Princeſs ſo charming, her natural Beauty being lately much augmented by a certain gracefull air and carriage which ſhe had learnt at Court, that he was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſible that he lov'd her more then ever. The great confidence ſhe repoſed in him, in acquainting him with her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret kindneſs and tenderneſs ſhe had of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe's</hi> reſpect made him diſcover of what an ineſtimable value the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Princeſs was, and caus'd in him an ardent deſire to poſſeſs it. And as his
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59724:34"/>paſſion was extraordinary, ſo it produc'd in him the moſt extraordinary effect ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, for it made him undertake to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver to his Miſtris the Letters of his Rival.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe's</hi> abſence caus'd the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> to become exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing penſive, and not hoping to receive any comfort, but from his Letters, ſhe inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly importun'd the Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> to know if he receiv'd none, and grew almoſt paſſionate with him, that he had not yet deliver'd her any. At laſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>receiv'd one, brought him by a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man belonging to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> which he immediately carried to the Princeſs, not to retard her Joy one moment, which was exceſſive at the receiving of it, and ſhe took no care to conceal it from him, but inviting him to participate of that which was as pleaſant as poiſon to him, ſhe favour'd him with the reading of the Letter to him, and the affectionate and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59724:35"/>witty Reply which ſhe made to it; this anſwer he carried to the Gentleman that brought the other, with the ſame fidelity with which he had render'd to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs the Letter which he had receiv'd, but with far more grief. Yet he comforted himſelf a little with thoughts that this Princeſs would make ſome reflection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what he did for her, and hop'd that ſhe would prove ſo gratefull to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, but finding her averſion to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe more, and more every day againſt him, through the ill humour which ſhe was in for the Duke of <hi>Guiſe's</hi> abſence, he took the liberty upon him to intreat her to be mindful a Little of what he ſuffer'd for her. The Princeſs whoſe inclinations were ſoly fixt upon the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and who found none (in her opinion) but him alone worthy to adore her, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented ſo ill that any other ſhould dare to pretend Love to her, that ſhe treated the Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> worſer on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59724:35"/>then ſhe had done at firſt, when he mention'd Love to her. And though his paſſion, as well as his patience, was extream, and had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to be ſo upon all occaſions, yet he departed from the Princeſs, and went to a friends houſe (not far diſtant from <hi>Champigni</hi>) from whence he writ to her with all the paſſion, which ſo ſtrange a procedure could inſpire him with, but yet too with all the reſpect that was due both to her Quality and Perſon, and by his Letter took an Eternal farewell of her.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs began to repent her ſelf to have diſoblig'd a man, over whom ſhe had ſuch pow'r; and being unwilling to looſe him, not only through the amity which ſhe had for him, but alſo through the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t'reſt of her Love, (to ſerve her in which his friendſhip was extreamly requifite) ſhe ſent him word that ſhe deſir'd yet once more to ſpeak with him, and that afterwards ſhe left him the liberty to diſpoſe of himſelf as he pleas'd.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59724:36"/>
            <p>Lovers are generally very weak, and are ſoon o'recome by any thing that bears but the leaſt ſhape of incouragement when once in Love. The Count obey'd her meſſage, and return'd, and in leſs then in the ſpace of one hour the Beauty of the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> her Wit, and ſome obliging words, render'd him more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive, and more her ſlave then ever. Nay he gave her too immediately the Letters, which he had but then newly receiv'd from the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time, the deſire which they had at Court to cauſe the chief of the <hi>Huguenot</hi>-Party to come thither, to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that execrable deſign, which was executed on St. <hi>Bartholomewes</hi> day, made the King (the better to delude them) to ſend away from about him all the Princes of the houſe of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> and of the houſe of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to <hi>Champigni,</hi> where his preſence ſerv'd but to o'rewhelm the Princeſs his Wife with grief.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:59724:36"/>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> retir'd himſelf in the Countrey to the Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain's</hi> his Unkles, where Love, and want of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, caus'd ſo violent a deſire in him to ſee the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſidering what he did hazard both for her and himſelf, he feign'd a journey, and leaving all his train at a ſmall vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage on the way, he took only with him that Gentleman, who already had made ſeveral journeys to <hi>Champigni,</hi> and took Poſt thither: and as he had no other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to make his addreſs to, but to the Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> he caus'd his Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to write him a Note, by which the Gentleman intreated him to come and meet him at a place which he appointed him.</p>
            <p>The Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> believing that it was only to receive Letters from the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> went and met him, but he was extreamly ſurpriz'd, and no leſs afflicted, when he ſaw the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59724:37"/>equalling his amazement. The Duke, prepoſſeſt with his deſign took no more notice of the Counts perplexity, then the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> had done of his ſilence, when ſhe related her Love to him. He began to exagerate his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to him, and to make him believe that he ſhould infallibly die, if he did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain for him from the Princeſs, the permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſee her. The Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> anſwer'd him coldly. That he would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Princeſs with all that he deſir'd, and that he would come and return him an anſwer.</p>
            <p>Their diſcourſe ended, he return'd to <hi>Champagni</hi> aſſaulted by ſuch various paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that ſometimes their violence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd him of his Reaſon, and he often took a reſolution to return to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> without acquainting the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> with his being there; but the exact fidelity which he had promis'd her ſoon chang'd that reſolution.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:59724:37"/>
            <p>He arriv'd at <hi>Champigni,</hi> without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he had beſt to do, but being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd that the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> was gone out a hunting, he went directly to the appartment of the Princeſs, who ſeeing him troubled, caus'd her women immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to retire, to know the ſubject of that diſorder: he told her (moderating his grief as much as poſſible) that the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> was within a league of <hi>Champigni,</hi> and that he paſſionately deſir'd to ſee her.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs at the relation of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected newes gave a great cry, and her diſorder ſeem'd to be little leſs then that of the Count. Her love at firſt repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to her the joy, which ſhe ſhould have to ſee a man whom ſhe ſo tenderly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; but when ſhe conſider'd how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary this action was to thoſe ſtrict rules of vertue which ſhe alwayes practiz'd, and that ſhe could not ſee her Lover, but by ſuffering him at midnight to enter her
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59724:38"/>appartment, ſhe found her ſelf perplext extreamly.</p>
            <p>The Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> (who attended her anſwer as an Oracle to pronounce to him either Life, or Death) judging of the incertainty of the Princeſſes reſolution by her ſilence, ventur'd to ſpeak to her, to repreſent to her all thoſe dangers which ſhe would through this interview expoſe her ſelf too, and being willing that ſhe ſhould perceive that he made her not this diſcourſe upon the account of his own int'reſt he told her. If Madam, after all which I have repreſented to you, your paſſion is yet more prevalent with you then my Arguments, and that you deſire to ſee the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> let not my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration (if that of your own int'reſt does not do it) hinder you from obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your wiſhes. I will not deprive a Perſon I adore of ſo great a ſatisfaction, nor cauſe her to ſearch for perſons leſs faithful then my ſelf to procure it for her. Yes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59724:38"/>Madam if you conſent, I will go this very Night, and find the Duke (ſince 'tis too hazardous to leave him longer where he is) and bring him here to your appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But by what way, and how, ſaid the Princeſs, interrupting him. Ah Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam (cry'd the Count) 'tis done alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſince you only deliberate upon the means, that fortunate Lover ſhall come Madam: I will bring him through the Park, give order only to one of your Women (in whom you moſt confide) that ſhe ſhould let down preciſely at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, the little draw-bridge which reaches from your Anti-chamber to the Garden, and do not diſquiet your ſelf about the reſt. Finiſhing theſe words, he roſe up from his ſeat, and without atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any further conſent from the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> he went out and took horſe, and went to find out the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who with an extream impatiency expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:59724:39"/>
            <p>The Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> remain'd ſo troubl'd at what had happen'd that it was ſome time before ſhe came to her ſelf again; but as ſoon as ſhe had recover'd the uſe of her reaſon, her firſt intention was to have had the Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> call'd back, and to forbid him to bring the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> thither, but it lay not in her power to put this thought in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. She imagin'd that without cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of him back again, it was only requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite not to let down the Draw-Bridge to ſpoil their deſign, and ſhe believ'd that ſhe ſhould have continued in that reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but when the hour of appointment was come, ſhe could no longer reſiſt againſt the Deſire which ſhe had to ſee a Lover whom ſhe judg'd ſo worthy to adore her; and ſhe inſtructed one of her woman with all, that was requiſite to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> into her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment.</p>
            <p>In the interim that Duke &amp; the Count of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59724:39"/>
               <hi>Chabanes</hi> approach'd near to <hi>Champigni,</hi> but in a very different condition; the Duke abandon'd his mind only to Joy, and to whatſoever hope and good ſucceſs, inſpires of moſt agreeable, and pleaſing into a Lover: but the Count, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, abandon'd himſelf over to diſpair and rage, which mov'd him a thouſand times (had not his honour, and the Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the action prevented him) to have thruſt his Sword through the body of his Rival. At laſt they arriv'd at <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigni,</hi> where they left their horſes with the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi>'s Page, and paſſing through the breaches, which were in the wall, they ent'red in the Garden.</p>
            <p>The Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> amidſt his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, alwayes retain'd ſome hopes that the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſiers</hi> reaſon would at length return, and aid her againſt her paſſion, and that in the end ſhe would take a reſolution not to ſee the Duke of <hi>Guiſe:</hi> but when he ſaw the Draw-Bridge
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59724:40"/>let down, he could then no longer doubt the contrary, and at that inſtant his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion grew ſo violent, and ſo unruly that he was ready to have executed the laſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of his deſpair; but recollecting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and thinking that if he made a noiſe, he ſhould apparently be heard by the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> (whoſe appartment look'd out upon the ſame Garden) and that all that confuſion would in the end light upon the perſons whom he moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, his rage (no longer agitated by the violence of his paſſion) immediately grew calm, and ſuffer'd him to accompliſh his deſign, and to conduct the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> to the feet of his Princeſs: where not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to be a witneſs of their diſcourſe (though the Princeſs teſtified to him, that ſhe deſir'd it, and though he wiſh'd it himſelf) he retir'd into a ſmall paſſage (which was contingent to the Prince of <hi>Monpenſiers</hi> Lodgings) being perplext with the moſt ſad and diſmall thoughts, that did
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59724:40"/>ever poſſeſs the mind of a diſconſolate Lover.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, though in their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage over the Draw-bridge they had been careful to make but ſmall noiſe: yet the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> (who through miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune) awak't at that inſtant, heard them, and caus'd one of his Gentlemen, belonging to his chamber, to riſe, to ſee what it was. The Gentleman put his head out of the window, and though the night was dark, yet through its obſcurity, he could diſcover light enough to perceive that the Bridge was let down: he adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd his Maſter of it, who preſently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to go into the Park, and ſee what was the matter. Immediately after he roſe up himſelf, being diſquieted, with thinking that he heard ſome body walk about, and came directly to the appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Princeſs his Wife, which was oppoſite againſt the Bridge.</p>
            <p>At the very inſtant when he approach'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59724:41"/>that ſmall paſſage, where the Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> was, it chanc'd that the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> who was aſham'd to find her ſelf alone with the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Count ſeveral times to enter in her chamber, but he alwayes excus'd himſelf, and as ſhe continued ſtill preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him, (poſſeſt with grief and paſſion) he anſwerd'd her ſo loud, that he was heard by the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> but ſo confus'dly, that the Prince only hear'd the voice of a man, without diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that of the Count.</p>
            <p>An adventure of the like nature had given cauſe of ſuſpition to a mind poſſeſt with more tranquility, and leſs jealouſie then this Prince: ſo that it ſoon produc'd in him an effect both of rage and fury, which made him knock with impetuoſity at the Princeſſes chamber door, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling aloud to cauſe it to be open'd, he gave the greateſt ſurprize imaginable to the Princeſs, the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59724:41"/>the Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> and this laſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Princes voice, ſoon apprehended that it was impoſſible to hinder him from being perſwaded, but that there was ſome body in the Princeſs his Wives Chamber, and the greatneſs of his paſſion repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, that if he found the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> there, the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> would have the affliction to ſee him mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd before her Eyes, and that the very life it ſelf of this Princeſs would not be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd from danger (theſe thoughts inſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with a reſolution worthy of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) he reſolv'd by an unparallel'd Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity, to expoſe himſelf to the Princes fury, to ſave from ruine an ungratefull Miſtreſs and a Beloved Rivall; and whil'ſt the Prince gave a thouſand knocks at the Door, he went to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who knew not what Reſolution to take, and committed to the care of the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſiers</hi> Woman, who had aſſiſted them to enter by the Draw-bridge, to conduct
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59724:42"/>him out by the ſame way, whil'ſt that he oppos'd himſelf to ſuſtain the Princes fury.</p>
            <p>Scarce was the Duke got out of the Anti-chamber, but the Prince, having forc'd the paſſage door, enter'd in the Chamber as a man poſſeſt with rage and fury, and who ſought an object againſt whom he might vent his diſpleaſure. But when he ſaw no body but the Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> and that he ſaw him remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable, leaning upon the Table, with a countenance in which ſadneſs was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in its lively colours, he remain'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable as the other, and his ſurprize was ſo exceſſive to find alone, and at mid-night in his Wives Chamber, the only man for whom he had the greateſt kindneſs in the world, that it ſo diſorder'd him, that it left him not the power to ſpeak. The Princeſs was laid down upon ſome Cuſhions, in a condition ready to faint away, and perhaps Fortune never repreſented three
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59724:42"/>Perſons in a ſtate more worthy of Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration.</p>
            <p>In Fine, the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> who could ſcarce believe his Eyes, and give cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to what he ſaw, but imagin'd it to be ſome fallacy, or ſome illuſion, and who had an intent to diſengage himſelf from that Chaos of confuſion in which this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture had invellopp'd him, and addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his ſpeech to the Count in a tone which ſhew'd that he yet retain'd a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for him; What is't I ſee (ſaid he) is't reall, or is't ſome illuſion? Is't poſſible, that a man whom I have lov'd ſo dearly, ſhould chooſe my Wife above all others to ſeduce her? And you Madam (ſaid he) turning to the Princeſs, was it not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to deprive me of your heart, and of my honour, without depriving me of the only man capable to comfort me in theſe misfortunes. Anſwer me either the one, or the other (continued he) and clear me from the ſuſpitions that I have
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59724:43"/>conceiv'd of an accident, which I cannot believe to be ſuch as it appears.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs remain'd unable to anſwer, and the Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> open'd ſeveral times his lips, without being able to bring forth a word, but at laſt, I am criminall (ſaid he) as to what concerns you, and unworthy of the friendſhip which you have ſhown me, but 'tis not after the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which perhaps you may imagine. I am my ſelf more misfortunate, and in a more deſperate condition then you. My death ſhall revenge you, of what I have been culpable of towards you, and if you will deprive me of Life preſently, 'tis the only favour which you can beſtow upon me that will be acceptable, and welcome to me.</p>
            <p>Theſe words (utter'd with a mortall grief, and an air which ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd his innocency) in ſtead of clearing the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> from his ſuſpitions, perſwaded him more, and more to believe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59724:43"/>that there was ſome hidden myſterie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd in this adventure, which ſurpaſt his imagination to divine, and his deſpair augmenting through this incertainty. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deprive me of life your ſelf (ſaid he) or give me ſome explanation of your words. I comprehend nothing, you owe this ſatisfaction to my moderation, ſince any other, but my ſelf, before this, would have imprinted characters of venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance upon your heart for ſo ſenſible an affront, and have ſacrifiz'd your life, to expiate your crime. The evidences are very falſe (anſwer'd the Count in inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting him,) Ah they are too viſible and too apparent (reply'd the Prince) I muſt revenge my ſelf firſt, and then ſearch out the myſterie of this adventure at leiſure.</p>
            <p>In ſaying theſe words he drew near to the Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> with the action of a man poſſeſt with rage and fury. The Princeſs fearing ſome miſchief would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low (which though could not well hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59724:44"/>ſince her Husband had no Sword about him) roſe to caſt her ſelf between them, but her faintneſs was ſo great, that it forc'd her to ſink under this endeaovur, for as ſhe approach'd the Prince her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſhe fell down in a ſwound at his feet.</p>
            <p>The Prince was yet more concern'd at his Wives fainting, then he had been at the tranquility which he found poſſeſt the Count when he approach'd him, and not being able longer to endure the ſight of two perſons who gave him ſuch cauſe for grief and diſcontent, he turn'd his head on the other ſide, and threw himſelf upon his Wives bed, orewhelm'd with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imaginable grief.</p>
            <p>The Count of <hi>Chabanes</hi> penetrated with repentance, to have abus'd a friend from whom he receiv'd ſo many tokens of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and finding that he could never make amends for what he had committed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted haſtily out of the Chamber, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59724:44"/>paſſing through the Princes appartment, of which he found the doors open, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended into the Court, took horſe, and guided only by his deſpair, he wander'd up and down the Countrey till at length he arriv'd at <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the interim, the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> who ſaw that the Princeſs return'd not from her ſwound, left her to the care of her Women, and retir'd into his Chamber, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with a mortal grief.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who was got ſafe out of the Park, without almoſt knowing what he did (ſo much he was troubl'd at what had happen'd) departed ſome few Leagues from <hi>Champigni,</hi> but he could go no further, without hearing ſome news of the Princeſs; which caus'd him to ſtay in a Forreſt, and to ſend his Page to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> what had ſucceeded that misfortunate adventure.</p>
            <p>The Page could not find the Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> but he learnt from others, that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59724:45"/>the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> was extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ill. The Duke of <hi>Guiſes</hi> diſquiet was much augmented by what his Page related to him, but without being able to hinder it, or to receive any comfort, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to return to his Unkles, leaſt he ſhould give them cauſe of ſuſpition through his longer abſence.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſes</hi> Page had indeed related to him the truth, in telling that the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> was extream ill, for the truth was, that as ſoon as her Women had got her to bed, ſhe was ſeiz'd with ſo violent a Feaver, and withall began to grow ſo light-headed, that from the very ſecond day of her ſickneſs, her Life was in extream danger, and her recovery was much fear'd.</p>
            <p>The Prince feign'd to be ſick too, to the end that none ſhould be amaz'd why he enter'd not into his Wives Chamber, but the order which he receiv'd to return to Court, whither all the Catholick Princes were
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59724:45"/>ſummon'd to exterminate the <hi>Huguenots,</hi> hope him out of the perplexity into which this adventure had plung'd him, and he return'd to <hi>Paris</hi> not knowing what he ought either to hope, or fear concerning the Princeſs his Wives diſtemper. He was but ſcarce arriv'd there, when they begun to attacque the <hi>Huguenots</hi> in the perſon of one of the Cheifs of their Party, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of <hi>Chaſtillon,</hi> and two dayes after was perform'd that horrible Maſſacre, for its execrableneſs, ſo famous throughout all <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The poor Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> who came with an intent to conceal himſelf in one of the remoteſt parts of the Suburbs of <hi>Paris,</hi> there to abandon himſelf over entirely to his grief, was invellop'd in the <hi>Huguenots</hi> ruine. The Perſons where he lodg'd having known him, and remembring that he had been ſuſpected to be of that Party, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd him that very night which prov'd ſo fatal to ſeveral perſons. In the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59724:46"/>the Prince of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> going out of Town to diſtribute ſome orders to keep all in peace and quietneſs, paſt through the Street where the murder'd body of <hi>Chaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> lay. At firſt he was ſeiz'd with aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment at the ſight of this deplorable ſpectacle, but afterwards his friendſhip re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving, it cauſed in him ſome grief, but the remembrance of the affront which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiev'd he had receiv'd from the Count at length gave him joy, and he ſeem'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented (without any endeavours of his own) to ſee himſelf reveng'd by For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe's</hi> thoughts being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with a deſire to revenge his Fathers death (and ſoon after being overjoy'd to have accompliſh'd it) his affection by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees began to diminiſh, and to grow leſs and leſs for the Princeſs of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> and he began to be leſs concern'd to hear from her then formerly, and finding that the Marchioneſs of <hi>Noirmouſtier,</hi> a Perſon poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59724:46"/>with a great deal of Wit and Beauty, gave him more encouragement and hopes then that Princeſs, he engag'd himſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely to her, and lov'd her with an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſable paſſion, which endur'd till death (which at laſt frees us from all our paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) put an end to their affection.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, after that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Monpenſiers</hi> diſeaſe was arriv'd to the height, it began to decreaſe, ſhe reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd again the uſe of her reaſon, and finding her ſelf ſomewhat comforted through the abſence of the Prince her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſhe gave ſome aſſurance, and hopes of her recovery, her health notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing return'd not to her but with great trouble, through the ill diſpoſition of her mind, which was again of a new perplext, when ſhe bethought her ſelf, that ſhe had hear'd no news at all of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> during the whole time of her ſickneſs. She enquir'd of her Women, if they had ſeen no body that came from him, and if they had
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59724:47"/>receiv'd no Letters, and finding nothing which anſwer'd her expectations, and which ſhe had wiſh'd for, ſhe imagin'd her ſelf to be the moſt unhappy Perſon in the world to have hazzarded all, for a man who in the end forſook her, and it yet prov'd a new addition to her misfortunes, to learn the death of the Count of <hi>Chabanes,</hi> which ſhe ſoon heard of (through the care which the Prince her Husband took to have her acquainted with it) and the Duke of <hi>Guiſes</hi> ingratitude made her more ſenſible of the loſs of a man whoſe fidelity was ſo well known to her.</p>
            <p>Such heavy diſcontents ſoon forc'd her to ſink under their weight, and reduced her into a condition far more dangerous then that from which ſhe was but lately eſcap'd, and as the Marchioneſs of <hi>Noirmouſtier</hi> was a Perſon who took as great care to have the addreſſes which were made to her taken notice of, as others did to conceal them: thoſe of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59724:47"/>ſo publick, that at as great a diſtance, and as ſick as the Princes of <hi>Monpenſier</hi> was, ſhe heard them confirm'd from ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hands, that ſhe could no longer doubt of her misfortune.</p>
            <p>This news prov'd fatall to her life, and now her courage grew too weak longer to ſuſtain the weight of her misfortunes, ſhe could no longer reſiſt againſt the grief which ſhe had to have loſt the eſtimation of her Husband, the heart of her Lover, and the moſt faithful'ſt friend that ever was. She dyed in few dayes after in the prime of her age, one of the moſt Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful'ſt Princeſſes of the world, and who without doubt had been the moſt happieſt, if Vertue and Prudence had but had the conduct of her actions.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
